this is from Samaya
5630 with
gavati at one time several bigus were
staying in the land of the chtis at
sahaji now at that time after the meal
on return from alms round several senior
biku sat together in the Pavilion and
this discussion came up among them
friends does someone who sees suffering
also see the origin of suffering the
cessation of suffering and the practice
that leads to the cessation of suffering
when they said this venerable gavati
said to those senior buikus friends I
have heard and learned this in the
presence of the Buddha someone who sees
suffering also sees the origin of
suffering the cessation of suffering and
the practice that leads to the cessation
of suffering someone who sees the origin
of suffering also sees suffering the
cessation of suffering and the practice
that leads to the cessation of suffering
someone who sees the cessation of
suffering also sees suffering the origin
of suffering and the practice that leads
to the cessation of suffering someone
who sees the practice that leads to the
cessation of suffering also sees
suffering the origin of suffering and
the cation of
suffering so it's not something that's
uh
commonly known is it because usually
there's a sort of a we naturally begin
with this assumption that we all know
what suffering is kind of thing um or
maybe some people also assume they
already know the practice the least the
sensation of suffering but they haven't
experienced the sensation for themselves
or something like that so they after a
period of doing the practice you get
this experience where you see the other
truths that you didn't see before but
it's actually more these things are so
um inextricably tied together that if
you see one you automatically see the
other one so first off with suffering
like um
it doesn't Define it there but you see
it in other places in the sutas it
defines it as basically any kind
of displeasure out of not it says not
getting what you want getting what you
don't want birth aging death
sickness um and finally it
says in short the five assumed
Aggregates are suffering
so you can can to some extent
know like everybody experiences aging
everybody experiences loss everybody
experiences these things but
seeing to the seeing suffering to the
full extent meaning seeing the five
assumed Aggregates as sort of a
phenomenon that's already quite um quite
an achievement that would put you in the
same position where you're able to see
all the other ones as well so um
and uh I think we discussed that in one
of the previous talks where we said that
uh there's a quote unquote right type of
suffering or suffering that that you
shouldn't be trying to get rid of um
just out of out of habit
because it's um we basically start with
the default assumption that unpleasant
feeling is what suffering is like
just as a result of that then anything
that that um manages or or ameliorates
your unpleasant feelings might seem like
it's an Escape from
suffering uh but that's because like the
definition of what's what you're taking
as suffering is already quite limited so
you can already see how that's a a good
example of how these things are tied
together so in the case of
craving um Haven clarified that if uh suffering
um Haven clarified that if uh suffering
is not un feeling then what would
craving
be what is the standard definition of
the origin of suffering right is
[Music] this is with us quite frequently I was a
this is with us quite frequently I was a
to say about
that well remember it talks about right
craving for sensuality craving for being
or existence and also craving for
non-being or
non-existence that that is the let's say
standard definition by the Buddha of
what is craving right those are the
examples of what craving is but
practically speaking what is the how
would you
define experientially what craving is
because usually you yeah you read this
this and it makes sense to everyone to
some extent like yeah what craving is
but as it says there if you haven't seen
the sensation merely on account of
knowing what craving is that means you
still haven't fully understood what
craving is so what I was thinking
is so what I was thinking
was you were talking about um negative
feeling not being what suffering is so
in that kind of approaching it from that
angle I would say craving is kind of
what creates friction with negative
feeling you could
say
um craving is what kind of de facto
turns negative feeling into suffering I
guess you could say it's what makes it
seem like
suffering and is it just in relation to
negative feeling well no it would be in
relation to the others
though I run the risk of walking into
the same trap that Sidi theas walked
into um because I was going to say even
when there is the pleasant feeling the
craving will still be in relation to a
negative feeling but that seems a bit
dubious um kind of a more General negative
um kind of a more General negative
feeling of like the undercutting like
anxiety of like oh I feel good now
but the anxiety of will I be able to
kind of maintain this will I stay this
way yeah so even when there's Pleasant
feeling there can still be the
recognition that that's
permanent it's not going to last and
even though the pleasant feeling endures
you still suffer on account of it not
being permanent which means which means
that there is still suffering even in
the presence of pleasant feeling so then
the goal of the practice is not to
artificially or through effort bring
about Pleasant feeling but bother to
know and to learn how to dwell
disconnected from all feeling including
the pleasurable ones yeah because as it
says it's it's the five assumed
Aggregates in general that are suffering
and it doesn't matter whether that setup
happens to be a pleasant setup it's the
fact that that it's the five Aggregates
mhm the fact that even when you tell
yourself you might sort of develop the
attitude that it's not yours but
fundamentally um unless you're an
Arun there is ownership there so you you
you can't just uh sort of uh deny it
through through a view it's it's you
have to actually go the opposite
direction and acknowledge that for as
long as these things are there you're
liable to suffering for as long as the
five Aggregates are assumed which is the
the starting position you don't have
like a on and off switch where sometimes
you have
um like the purified five Aggregates and
sometimes not so
so yeah from that point of view you
could say that
um again that that's not necessarily
something that's very profound or deep
it it it almost every Buddhist would say
yes I understand that uh craving is
suffering but the the trick lies there
in basically whatever you take from the
sutas it's always going to be an
interpretation but what makes you
really understand the four noble truths
is not when you have the same
information that the Su described
because anybody can have that it's when
that interpretation that you have aligns
with what the interpretation of the
Buddha had in other words that your
had in other words that your
understanding of suffering is actually
the suffering that Buddha talks about
fully and completely yeah exactly so
that for each and every noble Toth
basically that's why that's why it's um
it shouldn't
be practice shouldn't be done with the
assumption that that yes okay I already
understood these things now it's time to
just do them and then I'll get to this
result actually it's by refining
revising and correcting your
interpretation of what craving even is
for example that you would arrive at
stary um and uh and get to see the four
number tws so not like I operate with
the definition that I already have not
question it and then I just do this
practice on top of because that's really
just uh operating kind of within the
same understanding within the same even
if you get some results out of it um you
you haven't like left the the wrong view
that you started with so that's why the
bud said there is wrong
view I not understanding for Noble
Truths that results in wrong intention
that results in wrong speech that
results in wrong action and goes all the
way even to wrong Liberation MH in other
words you can liberate
yourself um from a limited ultimately
inaccurate craving because your
understanding of what craving was was
was inaccurate from the beginning and
you cannot when it comes to craving as the
cannot when it comes to craving as the
Buddha said like defilements cannot be
abandoned without knowing and seeing
what those defilements are first it
means that if you don't see craving
clear uh it's not like you can expect that uh
uh it's not like you can expect that uh
just doing the practice will so somehow
address that thing that you don't
clearly know because it's addressed by
knowing what it is yeah it's good to
make That explicit because even as the
sua says right when one sees one of
these Noble Truths you basically see
them all but there's still an order to
these four noble tools and the Noble
aable Path which is what people
generally take to be the practice is
actually the last one it's the fourth
one so it's so it's not that oh I'm
practicing the Noble atal Path in order
to come and understand those other Noble
TRS and find out what craving is and
what the sensation of suffering is you
know and until the four noble truths are seen
and until the four noble truths are seen
one basically doesn't know what the
practice is which means that you cannot
mechanically settle uh and continue doing what you
settle uh and continue doing what you
think is right because otherwise you
would have seen all all those four no
truths already so rather than
accumulating more information or
thinking that the four number tws are
the answer to a problem it's actually
more a question of as you just said like
inquiry and learning how to question and
uh be with the problem even if it is
unpleasant and basically learning how to
not move away from it because the the
the mental movement away from it will
inevitably involve craving for or
against the present situation that you
find yourself in and so it's it's only
by learning how to how to stay with that
problem that there will be a possibility
of understanding it and it is through
understanding the problem that it that
you can move Beyond it basically yeah
but if you think this is the problem and
now we need to run around trying to find
an answer which I'm going to reply to
the problem which also involves time
then and and then you assume that that
is the the noal path then that that's
already completely basically wrong from
the outset yeah it's it's as as others
to say as well the D has to be timeless
so it's not like you can just U yeah
like I I understand the problem first
and then I do all this and then the
problem is solved that actually that's a
that's a great exemplification of How
It's Timeless like if you see the
problem you already saw the dation so
it's um and and yeah as you said it's so
the the order of these truths is like
once you have seen the sensation of
craving um understood the formal truths
then you get access to this path which
will help you fully cement that
sensation of craving so that you never
go back to it and that's why it says the
the the sutas Define like the the stream
enterer and then the the Buddha defines
what it what is that stream and it says
it's the Noble eful Path so that's the
stream that they enter and then on
account of having understood what the
sensation already is they're able to
practice this path such that while
they're walking that path craving is not
there and then if they if they keep
walking that path keep developing those
factors then craving will never come
back so it's not a Time bound thing like
the craving is 90% And by doing these
things I'm decreasing it it's more like
while they are there
walking through that path craving is not
there but that's why it talks about the
underlying Tendencies so like during
that time that there's Right View right
resol or right
intention um craving is not there but it
can come back so as a matter of like
practicing these things as s to say for
seven years or 5 years or 6 months or by
sticking to this then then they get to
the point where so it gets to the point
where they're so familiar
with that sensation of craving that it
doesn't come back sensation of suffering
that that it doesn't come back so um
that's that's an important thing to
realize because also craving we should
understand that the it's not um
shouldn't be mistaken for like specific
states of anger or reversion or or
sensuality or desire because these are
more like the results of you not seeing
your craving and acting out of it then
then you get these these very coarse
sort of manifestations but really um
even when your mind is calm and
nothing's going on craving is still
there because craving is is really you
could almost equate it with ignorance
like craving just means not
understanding um feelings means craving
is there so even when it's just a
neutral feeling that nothing's really
happening nothing's really bothering you
the fact that you don't see um you don't
understand as the Buddha said the
gratification the danger and the escape
from these feelings means that there is
craving automatically yeah exactly so
and and again that's Timeless that's a
Timeless relationship and um so yeah that's that
relationship and um so yeah that's that
should be the practice like like and and
of course all of this becomes apparent
through the gradual training that that
comes before because um as we as as you
just mentioned you have to to some
extent expose yourself to that suffering
but that doesn't mean that you go around
doing you know self mortification
practices like like the some athetics in
Buddhist time were doing um you expose
yourself to the suffering by by just not
acting out of your desires doesn't mean
you need to go all the like Go the whole
way and and actually force yourself to
experience things you don't want to
experience like you know sleeping on a
bed of nails it's not when when there's
G
when your mind is greedy when when when
it's averse you don't act out of those
things and the right suffering as we
talked about will be there and that's
your your your time to start reflecting
on these things and trying to understand
without trying to get rid of it how do I
escape this suffering in that Timeless
way that doesn't require me to go
through this process of explaining it uh
rationalizing it or or sort of
psychologizing psychologizing or or or
or um doing something to get rid of it
but no like I directly see in that
Timeless manner what is the sensation of
that suffering as the Buddha said The
Liberation by mind and Liberation by
wisdom where those UNH wholesome States
cease without
remainder so um that's that that should
really be the criteria um for for like
to to be seeing from the start and and
that's why it's it's kind of painful
because it's more pleasant to just
assume that yes okay I got all this
right now I just need to do this
practice but going in that sort of more
personal way to to like not take
anything for granted and keep digging
keep digging further into your own views
um that part is is that's why you cannot
do it without faith because essentially
your that personality is inextricably
bound up with personality view so you
can't separate them so if you go dig
deeper then at some point it is those
personality view or views that will come
up for question which experientially
means that you bring yourself up for
question which is going to be unpleasant
yeah ignorance wants to survive and
obviously if if Enlightenment were easy
you know you wouldn't require Buddha to
to sort of discover the way out they
would sort of people would naturally be
T taking that direction but as he says
it's always against the grain
because um even when you're trying to to
find the way out of craving you can
easily slip into these attitudes of like
I said before trying to get rid of
things trying to manage your feelings
even though to you it feels like you are
practicing to to overcome craving but
actually that's a path of lesser
resistance than actually um enduring
things on the right level as the to say
which is the highest aestheticism yeah
that it doesn't say that the highest
aestheticism is like the person who
doesn't sleep doesn't eat doesn't
breathe doesn't do anything
it's it says it's patients or County
which is
the yes now can we say that the craving
or the desire to change or manipulate
things as you just mentioned that that
by definition means that the Aggregates
are already assumed like if if someone
would actually see none of these five
agregates are mine then why would there
even be the wish to do something about
them or to make them otherwise right so
but it is because it is not seen one aut
Al regards it as having something to do
with me and and once that's in place
me and and once that's in place
automatically the question is what am I
going to do about it including all the
practices which is going to be by
definition one but if somebody would
factually see those five assumed
agregates that are not self which is the
inside of the noble disciple then why
would he even be bother with those five
agates right and so the whole idea of
practices and development in a positive
sense like I'm here stuck with this I
need to do something in order to get
that which is the whole time bound
approach and then because the moment
there is that identification at once the
question arises what is the most
effective way the best practice the most
direct the highest this the most
Superior that right and then you get
trapped in this whole spiritual circus
of everybody offering you the most
powerful secret esoteric method to to
deal with your problem but it's all
based on on
on being already identified with those
Advocates if somebody were to actually
see that that's not the case then the
whole question of what is the right and
the best practice for
me yeah under goes I'm not saying it
fully disappears but um it it won't be
the same as basically when you start
yeah because as s to say it's um well
anything that's bound with time the
Buddha said um why should I seek what's
what's uh bound with time
instead of what's what's presently or
directly available which is a DH and so
anything that even if it's a spiritual
practice but but it's it's bound with
that expectation of I'll do this and
then something happens later yeah that
is a sensual principle in in in that
sense like if it's um getting rid of
because sensuality doesn't just have to
be um uh you know just course food music
and that sort of thing it's just the the
principle of of having pleasure and
sorry having pain and replacing it doing
something so that later that pain is
replaced with pleasure but the dhama
goes the other way around like
immediately in that Timeless sense with
when pain when pain is there you don't
replace it with anything but you don't
suffer either so that's that's the the
sort of paradoxical thing that that has
to seem paradoxical initially like um um
and and the the issue with what you said
like that people would make sense of it
like sure if I don't see these
Aggregates itself then I won't be
craving to do anything about them but
um it's also important to see that you
start by not fully seeing those five
Aggregates so you might be able to say
or you might say to yourself I'm I'm not
taking anything to self but you don't
see that actually the five arates go
deeper than that and you might be taking
your action not taking anything self as
self as it s to say that that's the
seeing not self itself in yeah it's not
a it's not a decision or it's not a
choice or decision because if it would
be like that then we can all just decide
right here now let's not take this AG
basically you can just decide to become
another another disciple it can be a
decision for like a so or higher and
that's why the Buddha would tell them
okay now regard for myself regard
feeling is not self yeah but that's
because they fundamentally have already
seen that they are not self so so in
other words he telling them practice
that path practice that no vo full path
yeah uh but before that it's more
important to to to like question
yourself with honesty and see wait no I
I still don't understand what even form
feeling is because as it said if I
already understood that which is the
first Noble Truth I would have already
seen the Escape so I wouldn't be like
you know seeking all these trying to
connect these dots to find the way out I
would see what the way out is just by
knowing what form actually is so just
ask yourself okay I'm letting go of
these things I'm practicing not self but
do I still have the expectation that
like okay so when is the sensation going
to happen that still means you're seeing
it in in that time sense of bound with
time it's not Timeless so so um that's
the thing like in the whole thing needs
to needs to start with that um
honest recognition of you being being
sick like needing treatment and then if
a patient just sort of the
first sort of they just take it U the
first medicine they take it just takes
the symptoms away and they assume okay
that's it that's enough um then they
won't they won't actually go to the root
of their illness so um you you can to
some extent have these release
experiences of what you might think is
not self but you have to keep in mind no
it's it always goes deeper than this
like there has to be more to this um and
that's where where a lot of people stop
like as soon as they're just able to
find some way of of managing their
feelings because they still on some
level assume that to be the problem then
okay yes that's the sensation of
suffering um so and that's why actually
the Buddha wouldn't even talk in terms
of stream entry or these four stages in
the beginning
it was more like um just cessation of
suffering and strife for that because
then it's very easy for for someone to
to find like a like a way that that
appears to get rid of the problem and
then they say okay well that's stream
entry so I won't keep that this is
enough for now I will keep going and
then um they can become complacent with
without actually having reached the the
the actual dentary but of course that
will not happen uh unless you're to some
extent already inauthentic or not
self-honest enough because you realize
no no I am actually
liable to craving in some sense so you
only fall into that mistake when you're
like actively when you don't have your
actively when you don't have your
priority straight basically when you
when you feel more put more importance
into like what you are what supposedly
stre whatever rather than no am I
actually liable to suffering or not yeah
I was going to ask just this like how
can one be sure that one is not just you
know managing still
feelings but telling oneself no no I'm a
Brut and
craving right because that's the
fundamental difference like management
by definition also takes time right but
as as you've just explained the practice
of the noble AAL path is otherwise so
okay one can W On's head around that
saying time time no expectations this
and that that's good but practically
speaking you sit in your room alone
we're assuming people have are keeping
their precepts they've introduce sens
strength into their daily life can you
just decide to stop managing your
feelings and just cramp your teeth and
then just right because now it's very
and then just wait for something to
happen which is which is very all
already take a wrong turn so okay that's
wrong so I don't wait so I'm not cond as
mine right because this is how it will
practically be so can we go into that
like can you decide to not manage your
feelings and is that in fact the same as
digging deeper as you said earlier well
it's it's all that's why the Buddhist
said there has to be these five factors
for someone to succeed in the practice
and uh the first one the first of all of
them is Faith so it's um it's kind of
that um
that that recognition that if you if you
don't have faith it's more like you you
just want to do things your way and the
first sort of
um occasion where you feel that
something solved the
problem you will stop there whereas if
you have faith you will see no no I
don't it doesn't matter like what this
if this seems like it works for me uh I
need to go to the root
to go deeper into the Buddha what the
Buddha actually taught for example so
without that faith is a foundation and
and self actually the other quality The
Bu also said it's it's self- honesty one
of the five essential qualities so
without that self- honesty I mean you
can give people various kinds of
definitions but fundamentally they can
always sort of find a room to or or find
a space to to just stop short of like
having overcome 95% of their suffering
but there's still 5% left and if they
have again like I said they don't have
their priority straight they're sort of
more concerned about feeling that
they're free from suffering rather than
actually being free from suffering then
they might just stop short and there's
even that suta where the Buddha says um
there's uh the simile of the hardwood
where he says it's like a like a person
looking for
hardwood that's what that's what they
want but they don't know what hardwood
looks like so then the first person um
sort of just takes like the branches and
leaves of the of the tree the other one
then goes a little bit deeper the other
one goes a bit deeper and all these
things he's talking about virtue um
talking about developing samadi
developing it says even knowledge and
vision so right understanding and the
Buddha says even that is not actually
the hardwood so then it's it's says like
the person would stop there because he
would he would be satisfied mhm with
just getting there so even like insights
and stuff and and factually getting to
understand um you know not the things
that are not in line with the suas but
actually know getting closer to seeing
the five arates and and such things like
you stop there you don't keep going um
then uh yeah you you like it says like
he he takes the sapwood which is like
right next to the to the hardwood and
then just leaves with that and then he
says somebody who looks at him would
would realize wait this guy doesn't know
hardwood looks like so whatever purpose
he wanted this hard for will not be
fulfilled so that's that can that can
happen like like if if you don't have
that uh that real kind of uh motivation
to to just not stop to not be satisfied
that's the B would say don't be satisf
ified with wholesome States M doesn't
matter how how
uh how accomplished you feel you need to
keep keep going and and keep questioning
and actually even u a noble disciple
it's uh it's not like they would um it's
not like they they their understanding
is perfect and now they just keep doing
the the same thing kind of mechanically
it's even in the Define somebody who
fully understands the truths so in other
words like somebody who has walked
somebody who the only person who fully
understands the path to the sensation of
suffering is a person who has fully
walked the path to the sensation of
suffering so so even a Sana or or any
other Noble disciple needs to even
refine their their view of what the
practice is even further obviously
that's like a 0.1% refinement compared
to all what they did before yeah but um
it's still like even they need that
Faith as suas would say and it would say
that if somebody doesn't have faith like
the or sakagami cannot become anagami if
they don't have enough Faith to kind of
see that okay I have this it's it's very
good and it is factually what the Buddha
taught but I can I need to still push it
further and question it and not take it
for granted and um and lastly about the
the last truth um
well you can even take the example of
like a mundane problem uh the more the
less clear you are about what a problem
is MHM the
more sort of uh alternative Solutions
you will feel that there are for that
problem and that's how you sometimes get
this view that that um there are many
different paths to the sensation of
suffering like not not in the sense like
you know how would be teaching
anapanasati to some people other people
would be teaching Brahma viharas not in
that sense no like completely different
views about what even craving is what
what mindfulness is that is basically
pre part yeah so so how to actually come
to see the Buddhist teaching that's a
that's a very pleasing view because you
know what works for you might not
necessarily work for me but if you start
out by thinking like that that is
already a compromise of the faith you
were just describing because you would
inadvertently be following your own
preferences but yeah if those if your
preference will be right then you
already wouldn't suffer yeah so at some
point you need to be prepared that you
have to go against your own views which
of course then at once raises the
difficulty yeah if that's the case then
how am I going to even find out what's
right well you don't know what's right
until you know what's right but
practically speaking that's also not
going to be very helpful but that is
actually how you are factually going to
on the terms with for example the factor
of
doubt you right so doubt can be easily
covered up by just settling mechanically
for certain factors but that's not going
to bring any results so one has little
choice but to upgrade one's ideas by
listening to those who know what they're
talking about I.E no disciples or ar and
if there's non available yeah then you
have to take
recourse uh from the sutas to to to find
that guidance right yeah but what what I
was what I was spe specifically meaning
was like
um the that that view you know like like
um there almost this implication that
like the more open-minded you are about
what the practice is MH that's better in
and of itself but if you think about it
in the sense of like when you're very
open-minded about what the solution to a
problem is that's because you're not
clear about what the problem is yes so
so like a doctor you know you have two
do you know you have a condition and
then you go to this Doctor Who says well
you can try this and if it doesn't work
for you then maybe try this other one
and if not well it's all relative you
know I don't it's up to you and then um
the other one says no this is what you
need to do and nothing else is going to
work now he might be wrong doesn't mean
automatically he's going to be right but
if one doctor actually knows what the
solution to the problem is it will be
one of the ones who are telling you that
it's something very specific because
that's like to the extent that you have
understood uh suffering craving and The
Sensation of craving that narrows down
to perfect
accuracy what the solution is what what
the path is so um so so because any any
whether you realize it or not any
practice that deserves to be called
different from another one it will
always be because it implies a different
view of what craving is and that often
happens with for example absorption
practices um the the the sort of even if
it's not stated the implied view there
is that craving is the presence of these
objects in my experience and so then by
not having those objects anymore
replacing them with other
objects you assume that you're
abandoning craving but really what
you're doing is uh managing your
feelings and so see it's not that it's
not just the fact that you still use the
ter the same terminology from the sutas
like craving and and foral Truth or
whatever that doesn't necessarily
mean that uh
that two people are teaching the same
thing even if they're using that
terminology because they can be pointing
at very different things with that
designation or that term craving for one
it's these thoughts that arise in my
mind that I just destroy and for another
one they might be telling you no no it's
a much more subtle thing it's an
attitude that you have in relation to
those things so then you you have to not
be too concerned with immediately
getting rid of them so that you can
actually get to discern that at ude and
so those two practices will not lead you
to the same place because they have a
different conception of what the goal is
yeah and also actually like a lot of
these key words are defined in the suas
that's that's another thing it is not
just that the Buddha talks about
Aggregates without ever specifying what
they are like you know people would
would ask feeling feeling or stream
stream or Consciousness Consciousness
and then comes some definition that can
still of course be misinterpreted
because as you said everything is an
interpretation but that can also be a
tendency to not Define things which then
helps to keep everything open so so that
you can get uh some sort of Quasi
justification for your own practice but
if somebody says well actually in the
sutas it's defined this way if you would
just stick to that then then half of
what you might think the practice is is
already denied just by upgrading your
understanding of what these words
actually designate yeah if you put that
first that would already make a big like
it will narrow down yeah you will still
have some to do some work for yourself
to clarify but uh it will significant
significantly narrow down a lot of
things but but um even then you you like
I've been repeating a few times already
like you make that practice out of um
upgrading your understanding of of what
these terms even mean like when I say
craving what is that in my experience
and the problem is most of the time um
the practice assume to be in in an
opposite direction
like I just read something about craving
is any sort of nebulous ideas I might
have about it that's okay now let me do
the the method the the practice and then
you don't see that all of that practice
that you're doing you're doing for a
goal that for something that you assume
to be the goal which might not be the
same goal that the Buddha was referring
to the think is that if you practice for
a certain goal that means that you know
the goal so you are actually already
there so think the other day like you
start from from actually there because
there is no point in like thinking like
oh but I know what the Escape of
suffering is but I'm not there yet no
you're actually already there so that's
where you start then you need to upgrade
that because those you don't go anywhere
but yeah yeah yeah you you're like I
said you might get new experiences out
of like cultivating that understanding
but um your overall view remains Remains
the Same you still
you haven't upgraded your your
understanding of the formable truths and
as I said even for a soana like he needs
to do that let alone somebody who
doesn't see the foral truth and then
they just keep that definition over just
10 years of the practice and and they
just accumulate these insights and
experiences but like all secondary to
that overall view that they had that for
example that craving is just these
thoughts that they get rid of through
through focusing or resorption or
something outside of that craving that
can be applied as an antidote whereas
actually it is the full understanding of
craving that that equals its sensation
yeah that you can antidote it with with
something else failing to see that all
of that what you're doing is is within
craving yeah because then the definition
of what craving is is like I said before
it's imprecise and that's when when the
imprecise and that's when when the
definition of the problem is
imprecise that's when then you get this
sort of um sort
of um just total mix of of random
practices that you do I do this one when
it works then when it doesn't work I do
the other one and do the other one
because again that definition imprecise
definition of what the problem is makes
it seem like almost anything can can
like when you're not clear about the
fact that uh your headache is actually
caused by brain
cancer uh you will be thinking that okay
okay yeah maybe a massage sometimes
works sometimes I don't know this herbal
tea also fixes the headache and then
other times just stress relief and
management fixes the headache um whereas
if you see no no the problem is brain
cancer you would see wait there's only
one solution to this because now you
have uh like clarified and narrow down
and pinpointed now this is what the
problem is yeah
so how is one practically then going to
correctly narrow down the
problem this now has to be the next
question right we we've just clarified
that um you know we can't just say any
anything goes as long as it's flat label
craving on it so if the understanding of
craving has to be accurate in order for
the practice to be the real practice how
then is one practically going to arve at
this most accurate understanding of what
craving
is to kind of come back to what we were
starting this conversation with the
feeling would it be safe to say that if
you haven't understood the four noble
truths then to some extent you are going
to still be thinking that feeling is the
problem so even if you kind of take the
view like yes craving is the problem
there might still be the
like well yeah there's there's The View
kind of under that which is that like oh
I feel bad right now because I was
craving and like you're still like like
you're kind of saying yes the craving is
like why I feel bad but the like feeling
bad is still where the suffering yeah in
other words being like you're seeing
that as the you're
calling inadvertently you're calling
feelings crazy right and that's why
that's why I mentioned it men with
saying like yes you're using the same
terminology but uh phology have the
right view you need to keep in mind for
you those terms don't mean the same
thing as they did for example for the
Buddha and then by keeping that in mind
you would never take for granted because
the problem isn't inherently that um
assuming or confusing feelings with
craving I mean everybody starts like
that so it's it's basically inevitable
the real problem is when you don't see
the practice being on that level
clarifying that and just assume because
you can see then if if if that remains
like a like a constant if that's not
being questioned then everything else
that happens will be just a management
of feelings as successful as it might be
while at the same time believing that
you are a rude and craving and that's
really the the where the where the
problem lies because if you were
practicing management of feelings
knowing that that's what you're doing uh
then there wouldn't be an issue because
then one day when you really feel like
okay no no I need to deal with it now
then you would turn to to as a b have
said to the noble search but no it's
when you think that you're already doing
the noble search on account of
management feelings even if you don't
call it that that's when it becomes an
issue so it's
um you would um you would get out of
that by again through self-
honesty if you have it really
established you would always be able to
see that
um that whatever you might be doing on
the level of managing feelings will not
free you from that liability because you
can say yes I even when you have that
implication that you just mentioned like
you're you might not be aware of it but
if you confuse feedings with
craving there will always be that tiny
possibility that craving sort of comes
by
itself where it will feel like
it and that's that's uh that's actually
implied in a lot of lot of times in in
sort of meditation techniques and stuff
it's like if I sort of don't catch that
mind moment properly or just something
happens that that you know I need to be
constantly on on watch to prevent it
craving might slip in by accident and
whenever there's that view there's a
misunder understanding between feelings
and craving because if you saw craving
you would see that there is no way that
this can happen by accident there is no
way that this can um just
come but where even if you call it
craving when you have that um like you
said I I I
feel like this because craving is there
and then I get rid of the craving for a
moment and then it comes back on its own
well that's a sign that you're most
likely just dealing with
feelings because the the feelings come
by themselves and the craving is a is a
is an answer we give
we it's already a reaction yeah towards
these feelings and it's fully within our
responsibility so that's why then the uh
full sensation of suffering is possible
because because if the craving were kind
of even like 1%
accidental then it could just come back
some time when when you don't expect it
or you get careless or something but um
it's it's because it is like you you
can't say it's it's uh you're just doing
it because then it from the initial
point of view that's not the case yeah
because it does have its momentum
already yeah so there's a question also
of
enduring craving which does arise but
then even then one needs to distinguish
that form feeling yeah so that's why
it's it's more accurate to say that it's
more like you're responsible for it
because if you say you're just doing it
then you might think like oh I just stop
it but no it's like you will be you will
be able to stop it at will once you
fully see it but initially you have to
keep more in mind like okay yes there is
this suffering in my experience and I'm
responsible for it and and I need to
find the cause if I just assume that I
can like stop it in a finger snap
knowing that I'm not a s yet means you
probably will be just uh again engaging
management so so yeah it's it's
um it
is always a result of ignorance that's
why I said it's you can almost take it
as synonymous craving and ignorance
basically like like synonymous so in as
much as ignorance can be
dispelled uh as light would would just
arise in a dark room as as the as the S
would say craving can be dispelled the
same way it doesn't take time
so you want to look at it that way and
not see it as like no no okay I do this
sort of meta practice for five minutes
and then the craving goes yeah so when
you switch on the light you don't need
to wait for the darkness to go yeah
exactly yeah and so the similar
principle is now with the craving say
that's why the Buddha that's why exactly
what the Buddha compared like the
arising of knowledge with with light
arising in darkness